<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in the parish-church of Aldenham, in the county of Hertford, on Thursday, April 16, 1696 being the day of thanksgiving to almighty God for discovering and disappointing a horrid and  barbarous conspiracy of papists and other trayterous persons to assassinate and murder His Most Gracious Majesty's Royal Person, and for delivering this kingdom from an invasion intended by the French / by Peter Newcome ... ; published at the request of the inhabitants of the said parish.</title>
            <author>Newcome, Peter, 1656-1738.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42212</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24419853</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24419853</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109695</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53084)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109695)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1708:34)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in the parish-church of Aldenham, in the county of Hertford, on Thursday, April 16, 1696 being the day of thanksgiving to almighty God for discovering and disappointing a horrid and  barbarous conspiracy of papists and other trayterous persons to assassinate and murder His Most Gracious Majesty's Royal Person, and for delivering this kingdom from an invasion intended by the French / by Peter Newcome ... ; published at the request of the inhabitants of the said parish.</title>
                  <author>Newcome, Peter, 1656-1738.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wyat ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Nehemiah IX, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109695:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached in the PARISH-CHURCH OF ALDENHAM In the County of HERTFORD, ON <hi>Thurſday, April</hi> 16. 1696.</p>
            <p>BEING The Day of Thankſgiving to Almighty God for Diſcovering and Diſappointing a Horrid and Barbarous Conſpiracy of Papiſts and other Trayterous Perſons to Aſſaſſinate and Murder His Moſt Gracious Majeſty's Royal Perſon; and for Delivering this Kingdom from an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion intended by the <hi>French.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſh'd at the Requeſt of the Inhabitants of the ſaid Pariſh.</p>
            <p>By <hi>PETER NEWCOME,</hi> M. A. and Vicar of <hi>Aldenham</hi> in <hi>Hertfordſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wyat</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109695:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109695:2"/>
            <head>TO THE INHABITANTS Of the PARISH of ALDENHAM, Who were Hearers of this Diſcourſe.</head>
            <p>IT was no little Surprize to me, after I had Preached the following Diſcourſe to you, to meet you all drawn up in a Body in the <hi>Church-Yard,</hi> ſo importunately requeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Publication,</hi> ſo much befides either my Inclination or Judgment. But, as hereby you ſeemed willing to manifeſt your zealous <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the preſent <hi>Government,</hi> and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered me an Opportunity of teſtifying the Sincerity of my <hi>Affection to you</hi> (who am wholly this <hi>Governments</hi> and <hi>Yours</hi>) ſo have I turned my Back upon all <hi>Objections</hi> (which I then urged upon you, and found afterwards
<pb facs="tcp:109695:3"/>
multiplying very faſt and thick upon me) to comply with your Deſires.</p>
            <p>If this <hi>Publication</hi> may contribute any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to the <hi>Government,</hi> and find as kind an Acceptance from the <hi>Preſs</hi> as it did from the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> (which is what I know better how to <hi>Wiſh</hi> than <hi>Hope</hi> for) To God be the <hi>Glory,</hi> to You the <hi>Thanks,</hi> and to my ſelf I own nothing more due, but the Charity of <hi>Prayers;</hi> which I deſire none of my <hi>Readers</hi> to refuſe or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, for the Succeſs and Encouragement of the weak Endeavours of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Labourer in Chriſt's Vineyard, <hi>P. N.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109695:3"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>NEHEM. IX. 17.</bibl>
                  <p>—And in their Rebellion appointed a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to Return to their Bondage—.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>UPON a Solemn <hi>Day of Humiliation,</hi> as the Remembrance of God's Mercies is thought, here in this <hi>Chapter,</hi> a proper Introduction to a more humble Confeſſion of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſins; ſo upon a ſolemn <hi>Day of Thankſgiving,</hi> a ſenſible Reflection on ſin, can prove no leſs proper Introduction to a more gratefull praiſing of God for his Mercies. For as the greatneſs of Mercy aggravates the guilt of Sin, ſo the greatneſs of <hi>Guilt</hi> inhaunces no leſs the greatneſs of Mercies. And therefore, as the <hi>Jewiſh Levites,</hi> on their <hi>Faſt-day,</hi> help forward their <hi>Humiliations</hi> by their Praiſes; ſo is it not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper for us now, on this our <hi>Day of Thankſgiving,</hi> to promote our <hi>Gratitude</hi> by our humble Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments. And as they introduced their <hi>Confeſſion of Sin,</hi> by recounting God's Mercies to them; ſo we may fitly introduce our <hi>Gratitude</hi> by reflecting on our Sins againſt God.</p>
            <p>And to this Argument doth the <hi>Text</hi> referr; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining an Acknowledgment of their Fore-fathers Guilt in an Inſtance that our preſent Age hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated, and occaſioned theſe our Thankſgivings for its no leſs remarkable Diſappointment.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109695:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Paſſage refers to the Story we read in <hi>Numb.</hi> 14 2, 3, and 4th Verſes. The People of <hi>Iſrael</hi> (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been miraculouſly delivered out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and provided for in the Wilderneſs, and ready to enter into <hi>Reſt,</hi> the promiſed Land) upon the return of the <hi>Spies,</hi> and their falſe Report, they fall a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, and not only fall out with the Providence of God towards them, but Plot <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt the Government God had in Mercy placed over them, and in a wonderful manner made inſtrumental for their late Deliverance: For <hi>all the Children of Iſrael murmured againſt Moſes and againſt Aaron; and the whole Congregation ſaid unto them, Would God that we had died in the Land of Egypt, or would God we had died in this Wilderneſs. And wherefore hath the Lord brought us unto this Land, to fall by the Sword, that our Wives and our Children ſhould be a prey? were it not better for us to return into Egypt? And they ſaid one to another, Let us make a Captain, and let us return into Egypt. And</hi> (accordingly our <hi>Text</hi> tells us, that) <hi>in their Rebellion they appointed a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> [at leaſt, purpoſed to do ſo, which in the Eyes of God is as criminous as if they had done ſo] <hi>to return to their Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was the <hi>Plot</hi> by them contriv'd, but by God graciouſly diſappointed in their own Ruine and Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>So that it hence appears to be no new thing (tho' very unreaſonable and wicked) for a People emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently ſaved and reſcued from <hi>Bondage,</hi> to oppoſe <hi>Themſelves</hi> their compleat Deliverance, and to be <hi>weary</hi> of Mercies before perfected to them: <hi>In their Rebellion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> deſiring and endeavouring to <hi>Return</hi> back to their former, already forgotten, Miſeries they groaned under.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109695:4"/>
            <p>A Caſe no more Unreaſonable and Impious than too exactly parallel to our own of this Nation; whom God hath, in like manner, but juſt ſaved <hi>From</hi> rather than <hi>Out</hi> of a <hi>Bondage</hi> (which ſurely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haunces the Mercy) and too many of us have (in no leſs aggravated a <hi>Rebellion</hi>) been plotting to <hi>return,</hi> and undo our ſelves therewith more irrecoverably a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>A moſt Prodigious, Unreaſonable, Horrid and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Folly, and Madneſs to a <hi>Proverb!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 26.11. and 2 Pet. 2.22.</note> (<hi>The Dog</hi> that <hi>returns to his Vomit,</hi> doing but what thoſe <hi>Rebels</hi> propos'd to do, who greedily longed after their nauſeated and diſgorged Oppreſſions) which as it ſtands upon <hi>Record</hi> to the reproach of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo will it doubtleſs be <hi>Chronicl'd</hi> to the ſhame of ſuch of this Age, with all that ſhall come after.</p>
            <p>Concerning it therefore (that ſuch as have any ways ſhar'd in the Guilt may be truly <hi>Humbled,</hi> and ſuch of us as have been bleſt in its Defeat may be truly <hi>Thankfull,</hi> and all of us do what lies in our Power to prevent the like for the future, by a more unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous and ſteddy perſeverance in our <hi>Loyalty</hi>) I ſhall inſiſt upon theſe Three things; Conſidering,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. The Evil and Folly of the Sin.</item>
               <item>II. The Inducements that may be accounted for thereto. And,</item>
               <item>III. The Duty incumbent on us for its preſent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointment.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>I am to account for the Evil ond Folly of the Sin:</hi> Which in the <hi>Text,</hi> was, That <hi>in their Rebellion</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God's Government by <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed (or <hi>plotted</hi> ſo to appoint) <hi>a Captain to return
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109695:5"/>
their Bondage</hi> they had ſo lately and wonderfully been thereby reſcued from<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And in its <hi>Parallel</hi> (wherein we are concern'd) is, That ſome, in like manner, of this Nation have <hi>in Rebellion,</hi> both to the Providence of God and the beſt of Governments, been Conſpiring to overturn both, and in the moſt lawleſs and baſe Methods deſperately to involve all in Miſery we have ſo miraculouſly hitherto been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved from. The Evil and Folly of both which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances is apparent in the very <hi>Attempt,</hi> much more in the the <hi>Fact,</hi> and moſt of all in the <hi>Conſequences</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Attempt was <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonable and Impious:</hi> As oppoſing the Deſign of God's Providence and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming upon its Aſſiſtance to contradict it ſelf. For as He was effecting and carrying on <hi>Deliverance,</hi> ſo were the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> here contriving again for <hi>Bondage,</hi> in confidence to ſucceed by the frail Inventions and Endeavours of Man, ſo as to overthrow what had been effected by the miraculous Power of the Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent God: And what could not be done without ſo many Miracles, they attempt to undo by their own Contrivance: As if God would work Miracles to make them again Miſerable, who had but juſt been at that expence to deliver them from Miſery! For how otherwiſe could the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> hope to get into <hi>Egypt,</hi> who got not thence without <hi>Manna</hi> to feed them, a <hi>Cloudy Pillar</hi> to conduct them, and a <hi>Sea di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided</hi> and dry'd up to procure them a Paſſage thro' it; which were all <hi>Miracles</hi> wrought immediately by God for them, and were neceſſary for their Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and without which (or ſome other ſuch Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances from God) their <hi>Return</hi> would be impoſſible. For they could not hope to get back without God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109695:5"/>
who were ſo much obliged to him to get thither, where they now were. And what an impious and unreaſonable Attempt was this in the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> to propoſe to do as much by their own Skill and Power, as God had done for them by Miracle!</p>
            <p>Nor is the <hi>Rebellion</hi> of the <hi>Male-Contents</hi> in our <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhort of a Parallel herein, who's Attempt was not only to overthrow a <hi>Revolution</hi> that was viſibly effected by an Over-ruling Providence, but to bring about another in oppoſition to it, wherein they muſt hope either to do as much and great things as God, without him, or preſume upon him to contradict himſelf, and to ſhew himſelf as ſignally to help their <hi>Return</hi> into Slavery, as he had done to aſſiſt their eſcape and deliverance from it; Both alike impious and vain to expect from God. For as Man is not a Match to oppoſe God in his deſigns, ſo is he not able to do any thing without his Aſſiſtance, nor can he reaſonably expect this in any thing that is not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Holy Purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Our late <hi>Deliverance</hi> was viſibly the work of God (impoſſible to have ever been effected, in ſuch a manner without an Over-ruling Providence) and is it not impious folly to Attempt the Undoing of it (as it were) in ſpight thereto; or to hope that God would ſo far contradict himſelf as, only for the grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of a few unreaſonable Murmurers, to go back with his own work and be ready to ſhew himſelf as viſibly in <hi>another Revolution to Slavery,</hi> as he did in that for our <hi>Deliverance</hi> from it; And what then is this in the <hi>Attempt,</hi> but a <hi>fighting againſt God?</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſſatisfyed with his Providences towards us, and preſuming upon his ſubjecting his Councils to ours; or elſe venturing to Act <hi>without</hi> and <hi>againſt</hi> him, by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109695:6"/>
undermining and defeating the declared Purpoſes of his Will?</p>
            <p>What the final <hi>Council of the Lord</hi> is, in this or any other Providential occurrence, none can tell; But what he hath diſcovered, and we can tell, it is not for us to oppoſe or be diſcontented with: much leſs to wreſt the work out of his hands, and of our own heads plot to <hi>return</hi> whence he hath brought us; which is to Oppoſe our Councils and Power to His; or rather to oppoſe him to himſelf, and is Illegal in the very <hi>Attempt</hi> both to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and to our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators. And much more then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The Fact it ſelf was Wicked:</hi> Being deſigned in an <hi>Illegal Manner,</hi> to an <hi>ill End,</hi> by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Means.</hi> For it is ſaid to be done <hi>in Rebellion,</hi> contrary to Faith and Allegiance engaged to the Government ordained by God, in oppoſition to Authority owned and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of by themſelves, and which was the Crime as of thoſe <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo of our <hi>Delinquents.</hi> For as they had groaned under <hi>their Bondage,</hi> and longed for free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom before Deliverance came, and thanked God for the ſame after they had it, and ſubmitted themſelves to the Authority by which God wrought it out for them; ſo no leſs did Theſe; whom no remembrance of their former fears, nor ſence of their late Joy in the <hi>Revolution,</hi> nor Obligation to the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (by Fealty ſworn or Protection accepted) could contain in due Obedience; But, <hi>in their Rebellion</hi> againſt Heaven and Earth, Intereſt and Duty, Vows and Obligations) they Conſpire the Diſturbance and overthrow of the preſent Settlement; not to Reform and Amend, or to proceed in our <hi>Deliverance,</hi> But (Oh ſtrange Madneſs!) <hi>to return to their Bondage;</hi> Reſolving to be Miſerable if they may not be juſt as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109695:6"/>
themſelves would be! To ſo ill a purpoſe do they do ſo ill! (and indeed an ill thing cannot be done other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) and ſo unreaſonable are the Projects of men, that regard not, or oppoſe the Council of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty!</p>
            <p>And then to bring about this; what is it ſuch ſtick at? The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed, <hi>in their Rebellion,</hi> the <hi>Text</hi> tells us, <hi>appointed a Captain to return to their Bondage:</hi> They would no longer ſubmit to Governors of Gods appointment; but would chuſe for themſelves, as more able and wiſe to do ſo (after all that had been done for them) to provide for their better Settlement. Which certainly, had Folly and Sin enough in it! But yet herein the <hi>Parallel</hi> ſeems to outrun the <hi>Original.</hi> For our Conſpirators have not only done this, but more. Intending not only to <hi>appoint</hi> a New <hi>Captain,</hi> and forſake and depoſe whom God had appointed for them, but Treacherouſly and Cowardly in cold blood, to Murder and Aſſaſſinate their old one (whom they had no fault to find with, but that he was not of their own appointment) whom alone God had made the Inſtrument of all their Bleſſings, and only from whom they could expect the continuance thereof to them.</p>
            <p>A Villany that no pretence, whatever, can be able to juſtiſy! That is not conſiſtent with the Principles of Humane Nature, much leſs of true Religion! And therefore henceforward the pretences of Conſcience muſt ſurely be ſtifled in a Cauſe that eſpouſeth ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcionable Deſigns.</p>
            <p>It is the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> s Doctrine that we muſt <hi>not do evil that good may come thereof,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 3.8.</note> [the moſt bleſſed conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences not being ſufficient to Authorize or Juſtify a wicked Deed] much leſs deſign evil for evil's ſake, and attempt a ſin in a ſinful manner, and Rebel for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109695:7"/>
Ruine: And therefore this alſo further illuſtrates and compleats the Evil and Folly of this Conſpiracy (both in the Rebellious <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and our own Countrey-men) That</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly. <hi>The Conſequences thereof were unavoidably Ruinous and Miſerable both to themſelves and the whole Nation:</hi> Becauſe it was not only a fruſtration of <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance,</hi> but a <hi>return to Bondage</hi> that was aimed at. <hi>Egypt</hi> and Slavery was to be the Conſequence; and a ſubjection to a Government, whence neither <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> nor <hi>Religion,</hi> nor <hi>Reward</hi> (which are the Deareſt things men have to be fond of) but only a <hi>Divine Diſpleaſure and Vengeance</hi> might reaſonably be expected.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The loſs of all Liberty was the certain conſequence of ſuch a Return.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.2.</note> For <hi>Egypt</hi> was the <hi>Houſe of the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites Bondage;</hi> the moſt grievous ſtate of their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, where they found no Mercy, no Compaſſion; But were treated as Enemies and Slaves, and ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to as many Tyrants as they had Governors; And therefore it was in vain for them to hope to be more at eaſe there, than where they now were, among men of their own Nation and Profeſſion, and under the Conduct of that Government whereby God had wrought Deliverance for them, and deſigned them Reſt and Liberty; and whoſe ſervice was nothing to the drudgeries of a <hi>Brick-kiln,</hi> or confinements of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> which they under went, and muſt again expect, if ever they returned into <hi>Egypt:</hi> Which of all Places, (having experienc'd its Cruelty) ought to be dreaded, and leaſt of all aimed at by them. So that Slavery muſt neceſſarily have been the Conſequence of return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thither.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:109695:7"/>
            <p>And no better, in Analogy of Reaſon, was our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> deſign'd to have been in (in reſpect to the <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> we have recover'd and now enjoy) from a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that exactly obſerves the Liberty of the Subject, to a Government that we experienced wofully Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and under which we could foreſee nothing but Ruine and Slavery. And therefore the Conſequence of this, muſt neceſſarily have been infinitely for the aggravation of our Grievances and increaſe of our Complaints; who, if we cannot be content to ſubmit to an eaſie and limited Government, that ſuffers and encourages every Man to <hi>ſit under his own Vine,</hi> and to poſſeſs and enjoy what he hath without Jealouſie or Diſturbance, ſhould be very unable to bear up under the Inſults and Oppreſſions of the Deſpotick Power of an irritated conquering Enemy. Therefore doth God threaten ſuch a Slavery as this as a Judgment to his People; <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.47, 48. <hi>Becauſe thou ſervedſt not the Lord thy God, with joyfulneſs of heart, for the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all things. Therefore ſhalt thou ſerve thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies which the Lord ſhall ſend againſt thee, in hunger, and in thirſt, and in nakedneſs, and in want of all things, and he ſhall put a yoke of Iron upon thy neck untill he have deſtroyed thee.</hi> From which, <hi>good Lord,</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue evermore to <hi>deliver us!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Nor is there more of Religion than Liberty to be expected in</hi> Egypt:<note place="margin">Exod. 8.26.</note> Where the Sacrifices of the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> were <hi>an Abomination,</hi> and for which therefore they expected to have been <hi>ſtoned,</hi> ſhould they have offered them <hi>before their Eyes;</hi> and inſiſted hereupon for the neceſſity of their removing thence into the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> for their Liberty in Religion, which the <hi>Egyptians</hi> abominated and perſecuted them for; and to whom therefore <hi>to return</hi> now again, was to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109695:8"/>
give up their Religion, or themſelves to ſuffer for it.</p>
            <p>Nor is the Malignity of our Adverſaries (from whom we are <hi>delivered,</hi> and have been conſpiring <hi>to return</hi>) leſs to be dreaded by us, than was this of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> by the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> towards a Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for the true uncorrupted Service of God. We have had long and repeated Inſtances of the impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Malice and Cruelty of <hi>Popery</hi> againſt <hi>Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm;</hi> which authorizes Princes to <hi>Dragoon</hi> their own Subjects (yea, and dignifies them with the Title of <hi>Eldeſt Son of the Church</hi> for encouragement to do ſo) and will diſpenſe with all the moſt ſacred ties of Oaths and Promiſes, for the propagation of their Faith and Suppreſſion of the <hi>Northern Hereſie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> (as they Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly Nick-name <hi>true Religion</hi>) If therefore we have any kindneſs for our Profeſſion, it will be impoſſible to be fond of thoſe that hate it, and once began to enſlave us for it; and from whom no Indulgence is to be expected there, any longer than it ſhall not lie in their Power to hurt.</p>
            <p>It was the certain proſpect of the impending Ruine to our Religion, that made us ſeek for ſecurity in a Deliverance; and therefore to Conſpire a <hi>return</hi> to our former (and much worſe) eſtate, is to betray this Security, and to Sacrifice our Religion to our Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion. For we cannot hope to be received with this which is an <hi>Abomination</hi> to the State we would <hi>return</hi> to: Nor can they be thought but to be weary of their own Religion, who would have the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Power of its worſt Enemies, and ſubject themſelves to thoſe that have eſpouſed the Intereſt of another Religion.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109695:8"/>
            <p>However, could it probably be thought that <hi>Egypt</hi> and Arbitrary Government would remit of the Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of their former Servants, and indulge a Religion they abominate (which is an odd Suppoſition to ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture much on) yet after ſuch an Eſcape and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it can very hardly be hoped,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That a Return would be able to ſecure a Welcome, but rather expoſe to Revenge and greater Miſery.</hi> For the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> eſcape coſt the <hi>Egyptians</hi> dear (by which they ſuffered both in their Eſtates and Lives) and would doubtleſs render it the harder for them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give; and if ever they had got them into their Hands again, have provoked them to have made them pay dearly for it; never truſting whom they had been ſo great ſufferers by; keeping a more ſtrict and jealous Eye to prevent the like eſcape again; ſuffering it no more to be in their power ever to hurt them again, than they would be ſure to take care of ever encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging them thereto by connivance or kindneſs. <hi>A provoked Enemy can never make a good Friend.</hi> And therefore <hi>Iſrael</hi> s return into <hi>Egypt</hi> could no more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelves, than it would oblige their Enemies.</p>
            <p>And yet <hi>Iſrael</hi> might as reaſonably think to make Peace with <hi>Egypt</hi> as we with <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> whoſe Deſigns We (and God for us) have hitherto ſo vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly oppos'd, and ſucceſsfully broken all their Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures. Into whoſe Power could we, upon any Terms, but be once reduc'd (which God forbid!) both <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> and <hi>Inclination</hi> would quickly break all to work our final Deſtruction. For <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Perſecution</hi> is the very Genius of <hi>Popery.</hi> It is <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Conſtitution to oppreſs; neither is it alter'd ſince we were delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from it; nor would our <hi>Return</hi> thither change or abate its Temper to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> eſpecially, who have ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109695:9"/>
it. 'Tis not ſafe truſting to a reconciled Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, who will continue reconciled but till he can have an opportunity to do Revenge. And this preſent <hi>French</hi> King, that was ſet in his Throne by his Proteſtant Subjects, did therefore, 'tis ſaid, make this his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their Deſtruction, <hi>That they, who had power to ſet him up, might not be in a capacity to uſe it to pull him down again:</hi> And ſhould then the preſent Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and Malignity among us have took effect to have reſtor'd us to our <hi>Egyptian Bondage,</hi> to be ſure it would quickly have been taken out of our Power ever to have deliver'd our ſelves again; and ſo our <hi>Return</hi> muſt neceſſarily have been to far greater Miſeries than we eſcap'd from. Beſides,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly, <hi>The Diſpleaſure and Vengeance of God, that undoubtedly follows, and falls juſtly upon ſuch perfidious Revolters.</hi> For the <hi>Falſe Spies</hi> (who were the chief Conſpirators) died by the Plague preſently, and God cuts off by degrees all the murmuring <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and delays the National Mercy forty Years, till they were all dead that deſpiſed it, and raiſes up a new Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to inherit the Bleſſings they had forfeited.</p>
            <p>Mercies deſpiſed are ſeldom perfected; and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Ingratitude of a preſent Age, may render themſelves unworthy of Bleſſings deſigned and begun for them, and deferr them to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>God will not let one of thoſe enter into the <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Land of Canaan,</hi> that had been any ways conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to a <hi>Return</hi> into <hi>Egypt.</hi> He will neither bleſs them with what he <hi>purpoſed,</hi> nor gratifie them with what they <hi>deſired,</hi> but dooms them Vagabonds, to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out their Lives in a <hi>Wilderneſs:</hi> Or had he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted their <hi>Return,</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> had receiv'd and che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd them, yet even there could he have ſent after
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109695:9"/>
them, and have deſtroyed them for their backſliding, and have made them more miſerable in the <hi>Succeſs,</hi> than he did in the Diſappointment of their Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy.</p>
            <p>'Tis fatal to throw off the ſafe and wiſe conduct of Providence, which we never oppoſe or direct, but to our own loſs. God will not indure to be controuled by us; neither will he ſuffer ſuch Preſumption to eſcape ſome mark of his heavy Diſpleaſure. No Age is without its Monuments of Sufferings for turbulent rebellious Diſcontent. And that in ours, ſuch are now erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is but the uſual and juſt Reward of the ſame Sin.</p>
            <p>Upon which Accounts, ſo great is the <hi>Madneſs,</hi> ſo grievous the <hi>Guilt</hi> of Oppoſing or Rejecting the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils of the Lord</hi> by the Rebellious <hi>Devices of Men!</hi> which is ſo unreaſonable in the <hi>Attempt,</hi> ſo wicked in the <hi>Fact,</hi> and ſo very pernicious in its <hi>Conſequences;</hi> that tends to the loſs of <hi>Liberty,</hi> the extirpation of the <hi>True Religion,</hi> the mercileſs <hi>Revenge of an inſulting Enemy,</hi> and the unavoidable Judgments of a Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, Juſt, and Jealous Deity! And yet ſuch was the Guilt and Folly of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> in Conſpiring to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> to <hi>Egypt,</hi> after their eſcape from their <hi>Bondage</hi> in it; and ſuch, no leſs, of our preſent Age, in its unreaſonable <hi>Murmurers</hi> under the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Rebellious Attempts that have been now diſcovered and diſappointed of their Conſpiracy, <hi>to return to their Bondage</hi> they had ſo lately been ſet free from.</p>
            <p>Nor is the <hi>Folly</hi> more Parallel than the <hi>Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in both thereto. For as their <hi>Sin</hi> ſeems too much alike, ſo is the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of it. And therefore conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der we alſo now (which is our next Particular pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd, <hi>viz.</hi>)</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:109695:10"/>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>The Inducements that may be accounted for that betray'd to ſuch Villany.</hi> For the greater the Sin, the greater the Wonder what ſhould draw Men into it. That ſo Helliſh a Motion ſhould meet with ſo ready a Reception, and gain to it ſelf ſo ſtrong a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with ſo much conſent among a People ſo highly favoured, ſo lately delivered, ſo ſignally protected, by wonderful Providence! A People that ſaw all God's Judgments againſt <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the Overthrow of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and all his Hoſt, for their Succour, and without their help! Who found themſelves ſecur'd (by the Defence and Conduct of a Cloud and Fire, by the plentifull and wholſome proviſion of <hi>Manna</hi> from Heaven, and the miraculous Water from a Cloven Rock) from all the inconveniencies of a barren and perilous Wilderneſs, and were juſt ready to enter the promiſed Land, and within ken of a moſt deſirable Settlement; and yet, after all this, to fruſtrate and daſh at once, what had been ſo long, and with ſo great Expence and miraculous Succeſs adoing towards their Felicity, and to attempt, in ſo rebellious a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, to <hi>return</hi> to Miſery: As incredible as this ſeems, yet ſo it was, and ſo it may be again, if it may not be ſaid (upon too like <hi>Inducements</hi>) that ſo it now is; (the like Account being to be given for the like Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion now as then) for thus it ſeems to have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>From the falſeneſs of the Spies;</hi> who by an evil Report diſcourage the People, and prejudice them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Truth and Encouragements that they were employed to have laid before them. For they are ſent into the good Land, to ſee the goodneſs thereof, and to make their Report according to what they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109695:10"/>
ſaw. And <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Caleb</hi> (who were of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and knew as much as any of them) accordingly make their Report faithfully; but the reſt falſifying, conceal their Encouragements, and raiſe Difficulties, and propagate Lyes to ſerve their own Deſign, and fruſtrate the Mercies deſigned for them.</p>
            <p>Nothing uſually doth more miſchief in a State, than the ſpreading of falſe and evil Reports in it; and were it not from the falſeneſs of <hi>Spies,</hi> there would be no colour for <hi>Conſpiracies;</hi> (all Rebellions againſt a Government being founded on its miſrepreſentations.) 'Tis an evil Report that makes Men evil minded; and 'tis the officiouſneſs of deſigning <hi>Spies,</hi> that prejudices the People. Had all Men ſpoke as they had found, and regarded Truth more than Paſſion and Self-intereſt in their Repreſentations, it would not have been likely for any to have deſired ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den a change of a Government to which all have been ſo very much beholden. But we have had <hi>Falſe Spies</hi> among us, who have made it their buſineſs to raiſe and propagate <hi>evil Reports;</hi> (magnifying the Strength and Advantages of our Enemy, and leſſening that of our own; meeting to murmur in their Tents; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves glad at our Loſſes, and diſturb'd at our Advantages; inſiſting upon Difficulties to make them Impoſſibilities; working under-hand to obſtruct and betray Affairs, and then making it a prejudice to the Government, that things ſucceed no better, and urging the People to grumble at their Circumſtances, which themſelves induſtriouſly do all they can to hinder from being amended:) Such are the evil Inſtruments of our publick Diſturbances, that draw off the Minds of Subjects from their Duty of Allegiance, and run them upon the moſt deſperate and ruinous Attempts
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109695:11"/>
to croſs the Providence of God, and contrive for the diſappointment of Bleſſings deſign'd for them. From the <hi>evil Reports</hi> that are falſly ſpread, by ſome diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented deſigning <hi>Spies</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> ariſes the unreaſonable Conſpiracy <hi>to return into Egypt.</hi> And which is alſo promoted,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>From an evil Heart of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief.</hi> A miſtruſt of God's Power and Goodneſs to make good his Promiſe, utterly incapacitating for the benefit of its Completi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.<note place="margin">Heb. 3.19.</note> For ſo the <hi>Iſraelites entred not in becauſe of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief:</hi> God being provoked to leave them who firſt leave him, and to ſuffer them to fall by their own Councils, who have not Faith to depend on his. God is able and willing to carry on his own work, and Man is never neceſſitated to his own ſhifts. But <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief</hi> is full of Suſpition, that makes Men uneaſie and reſtleſs <hi>to lean to their own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings,</hi> tho' never ſo infirm and deceitful, rather than to the Conduct of a wiſe Providence, tho' never ſo Omnipotent and Faithfull. Therefore when Difficulties ariſe, which may be deſign'd to try and exerciſe <hi>Faith</hi> (which, ſtanding tryal, is certainly the moſt prevalent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement of Omnipotency to overcome ſuch Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties for us) then <hi>Hope</hi> is deſerted, and <hi>Faith made ſhipwrack of,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> begins to argue againſt all <hi>Reaſon: He that hath done That, can do This;</hi> ſo <hi>Faith</hi> argues;<note place="margin">Pſ. 78.19, 20.</note> but <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief</hi> ſays, <hi>He hath indeed done That, but can he do This alſo? Can God furniſh a Table in the Wilderneſs? Behold he ſmote the Rock, and the Waters guſhed out, and the Streams overflowed. Can he give Bread alſo? can he provide Fleſh for his People?</hi> Such is the <hi>Logick</hi> of <hi>Infidelity,</hi> that never wants Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt Providence, and renders every Objection inſuperable, to the littling of God upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109695:11"/>
To its Carnal eye, the work gloriouſly begun, can never be perfected. As if God that had done, could do no more; or that any thing that was to be done, was greater than what had been done! As if God, who had Plagued <hi>Egypt,</hi> Overthrown <hi>Pharaoh</hi> with all his Hoſt, and ſo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly reſcued the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> Could not as eaſily drive out the <hi>Canaanites</hi> before them; But that they were now come to their <hi>Nè plus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltra,</hi> and had already advanced as far as God could conduct them, and were neceſſitated to ſhift at laſt for themſelves, and <hi>appoint them a Captain to return to their Bondage!</hi> As if the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>People that dwelt in the Land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 15.28.</note> was too great for God to conquer for them; or their <hi>Walled Cities</hi> more impoſſible to be ſcaled, than <hi>a Sea</hi> to be walked through on foot dryſhod! Alas! What are the <hi>Children of Anak</hi> more in God's hands, than the <hi>Egyptians!</hi> who can as eaſily and ſpeedily ſqueeze their <hi>Grand Monarch,</hi> as we have heard they have inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly a poor <hi>Orange.</hi> As if it were a greater thing for God to <hi>Settle</hi> a Nation than to <hi>Deliver</hi> it! And finally, as if He that had broken ſo oft the <hi>Deſigns of France</hi> upon us, could not, in the end, break the <hi>Power of France</hi> for us; But we muſt now ſhift for our ſelves; And, to attone for what hath been done, endeavour to undo all again; and <hi>return</hi> our ſelves <hi>into Bondage</hi> (thro' a miſtruſt that our Deliverance cannot be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured to us) in oppoſition to God's Providence and our Duty: Wreſting the diſpoſal of affairs out of his hands: Commiting our ſelves no longer to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; but <hi>in Rebellion,</hi> in Treachery, Violence and Villany, force our way back, as not believing we can go any longer proſperouſly forward.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109695:12"/>
            <p>Hence it is men make ſo many difficulties and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances to themſelves, and then run upon ſo many unreaſonable extravagances to avoid them. <hi>To him that believes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 9.23.</note> 
               <hi>all things are poſſible;</hi> and to them that once begin to miſtruſt God nothing ſeems probable. So that 'tis evidently <hi>Infidelity</hi> that makes men reſtleſs and <hi>murmuring</hi> under their preſent circumſtances, and runs them upon ſuch impious and fooliſh Deſigns, as are Unreaſonable in the <hi>Attempt,</hi> Wicked in the <hi>Fact,</hi> and Deſtructive in the <hi>Conſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A further (and no leſs juſtifyable) account of the ſin before us, may alſo be given,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>From an unreaſonable Prejudice, Envy and Spite againſt the Perſon God hath made, here, both Deliverer and Governour.</hi> A wicked People cannot heartily love a good Governour; not for any evil they fear from ſuch, but becauſe of the good they malign in them. <hi>They envyed Moſes in the Camp,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106.</note> 
               <hi>and Aaron the Saint of the Lord.</hi> They will not be ſaved by thoſe they hate, whoſe ſucceſſes increaſe their hatred; and are all for returning to the <hi>Tyranny of Pharaoh,</hi> rather than be obliged to their greateſt Benefactor, and ſubmit to the Government of God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Meekeſt of Men.</hi> Thus <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> and <hi>Ariſtides</hi> were both driven out of their Country,<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> only for their eminent ſervice for it. The Praedominancy of Vice cannot indure the Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Vertue. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would hardly ever have thought of <hi>Egypt</hi> for their <hi>Aſylum,</hi> were it not for good <hi>Moſes,</hi> whom they cannot love becauſe he is holy and good and would have them be ſo too, and will not ſuffer them in their badneſs. Therefore to gratify Revenge and indulge Spight, is Slavery to the worſt of Tyrants preferr'd to Security and Liberty under the moſt gentle Government that ſeeks our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109695:12"/>
Good, and would make us Good. And this further ſuggeſts another Reaſon of ſo Unreaſonable an At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt; Even<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly. <hi>From an Impious malignity and ſeeming dread of being Reformed from our Vices.</hi> For <hi>Egypt,</hi> tho' <hi>an Houſe of Bondage</hi> to their Bodies, was yet a Freedom to their Luſt's; Where no religious Reſtraints were laid upon them; but ſo they performed their Duty to their <hi>Task-Maſters,</hi> they had not only Liberty but Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to neglect and deſpiſe the ſervice of God: Whereas the preſent Government they were under had procured them ſtrict Laws and Holy Statutes, and put them in Execution for the promotion of Piety and Religious Exerciſes; and tho it had free'd them from Bodily Slavery, yet it reſtrain'd them ſinful Liberty; And if ever they were come to be ſetled in their <hi>Land of Reſt,</hi> they knew they were to expect more ſtrictneſs and ſeverity in Religious matters; which was very ungrateful to corrupt Nature, and made them wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to turn their backs on <hi>Canaan</hi> rather than on their <hi>Luſts,</hi> and prefer Slavery in <hi>Egypt</hi> before the ſervice of God in <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How much this impious Motive may have influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd the Revolters in our <hi>Iſrael<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> (tho' it be not Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to judge, yet) it is too apparent not to be took notice of, from the profeſſed looſneſs and vicious Lives of the Majority of thoſe who have all along appeared moſt disaffected to this preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. All may pretend Conſcience, but few of them have afforded us the teſtimony of a good Life for their regard to any.</p>
            <p>God be Thanked! <hi>The Rebellion</hi> is not ſo General a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, as it was among the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> But one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve thoſe who have been concern'd in it,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109695:13"/>
to be the very worſt of Men (<hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts;</hi> Men of the worſt, or Men of no Religion) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt likely to be induced thereto, from their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to Vertue and fears of Reformation.</p>
            <p>Such then is the Impiouſneſs of the Villany, and the Unreaſonableneſs of the Inducements which may be ſuppoſed to lead to it. We are next of all to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider (as briefly as may be)</p>
            <p n="3">III. Laſtly. <hi>The Duty now incumbent on us for its preſent diſappointment.</hi> And that ſurely is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To deteſt and diſclaim the Guilt of ſuch Sin.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the more malignant the Plague, the further di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will every man in his wits endeavour to flee from it. No Wiſe nor Good man but would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be defiled by his too near approach to ſuch filthy Practices. A Villany of ſuch groſneſs can not be decry'd nor declaimed too much againſt. The very occaſions of it ſhould henceforward be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable to us. Neither can it become us now to ſit <hi>Neuter,</hi> much leſs to <hi>approve,</hi> but to <hi>oppoſe</hi> our ſelves to the Cauſe that needs or countenances ſuch unjuſtifyable Courſes. And ſince there is ſuch Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny among us, it concerns us the rather to diſtinguiſh our ſelves, by readily <hi>Aſſociating</hi> with thoſe that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim it; by ſedulouſly clearing our ſelves from all ſuſpicions that we may formerly have lain under; and entring our Proteſtations againſt approving or abetting, or any way being concern'd in ſo foul a Crime. And yet, tho' we never ſo much Deteſt the Crime, we ſhould hence be moved alſo</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To Compaſſionate and Pray for ſuch as are involved in it.</hi> Becauſe the more hainous the Guilt, the more wretched the Sinner, and the more an object of our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109695:13"/>
Pity and Interceſſions to God for him. That Humane Nature ſhould be ſo ſtain'd, is Deplorable: That any of our Fellow-Creatures ſhould ſo abuſe Reaſon and Conſcience is more ſo: But that our Fellow-Subjects and Chriſtians ſhould be ſo devoid of Grace and Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity is moſt of all ſad and miſerable. In ſuch, we ſee the Miſery Sin expoſes to, and the Weakneſs of Nature to preſerve it ſelf, and the great dependance we have continually on the preventing and aſſiſting Grace of God; And if others fall while we ſtand, it is not becoming ſuch as we are to be <hi>high minded,</hi> but the rather to <hi>fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such ſins therefore of others ought to make us more careful over our ſelves, and to compaſſionate their Miſcarriages to which we were ſo obnoxious our ſelves. No man's Misfortune deſerves our Inſults, tho' the Occaſion may juſtly our blame. His <hi>Sin</hi> that made him miſerable is to be deteſted, but the <hi>Miſery</hi> it makes him ſuffer deſerves our Pity.</p>
            <p>It now therefore becomes us to Compaſſionate the Guilt and Sufferings, which the unbridled Madneſs and Blindneſs of theſe Sinners hath inſnared them in; and to recommend their Misfortune to the God of Pity, to open their Eyes to a due ſence of their Error, and to break their Hearts into a ſincere Contrition for their Guilt, and to fit them for, and ſupport them under, and ſanctify to them the ſufferings they have procured to themſelves in this World, ſo as to avoid thoſe eternal Torments they have reaſon to expect, otherwiſe, will await them in the next World.</p>
            <p>Neither, while we are thus concern'd for <hi>Their Sin,</hi> ought we to be unmindful of our own. And, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, further, hence it becomes us alſo</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:109695:14"/>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>To be Humbled for our own ſins, which have threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten'd us with ſuch a Judgment from other men's.</hi> For it is for <hi>Thoſe</hi> that God permits <hi>Theſe</hi> to threaten or afflict us with an Injury; He deſigning our <hi>Puniſhment</hi> by their <hi>Guilt.</hi> And therefore now we ſee the Danger and Ruin we were brought juſt upon the Brink of, by others Treachery; it ſhould make us reflect upon our own Guilt that hath provoked God to raiſe up ſuch turbulent and falſe Rebels among us, and permitted them to deſign and carry on their Conſpiracy ſo far, as to endanger our <hi>Liberty, Laws</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> thereby. The <hi>Fault</hi> is theirs, but the <hi>Warning</hi> is ours. And tho' our <hi>Reprieve</hi> is obtain'd, yet nothing but an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Repentance can ſecure us a Pardon.</p>
            <p>The Danger we were in is graciouſly diſcover'd to us, to let us ſee our demerits, and to provoke us to a Reformation, which is the only Terms upon which we may promiſe to our ſelves ſafety; without which God can eaſily reduce us into the like or worſe dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and deny us any more ſuch Deliverance. Our Enemie's <hi>Diſappointment</hi> then, muſt be our Warning; leſt our continued impenitency may give them <hi>Succeſs</hi> againſt us, for the Puniſhment of our Sins which their Diſappointment could not warn us to Reform. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is not ſo much the <hi>Injury</hi> they deſign'd us, as our <hi>Sins,</hi> that provoked God to permit them to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign any againſt us, that (upon ſuch Diſcovery and Diſappointment) we ought chiefly to oppoſe our ſelves, and be humbled for.</p>
            <p>God will preſerve us, if we will not be wanting to preſerve our ſelves from Sin; which is the only Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my we need to fear; and which we have a great deal of Reaſon to fear, even from an Apprehenſion of the Miſeries it ſo lately threaten'd us with, and had cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109695:14"/>
executed upon us, had not God ſtept in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween, to ſave us yet longer from long ſince deſerved Deſtruction. 'Tis fatal to perſiſt in ſuch Provocations. And, having received yet another Deliverance, it the more concerns us, now at length, to be more wary of preſuming to weary out Divine Patience to no purpoſe, and to <hi>Sin</hi> now <hi>no more, leſt a worſe thing come</hi> next <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us.</hi> And hence, then, how can we but own our Obligation further,</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>To be truly Thankful to God for our preſent Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> It being only his Mercy and undeſerved For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance towards us, that hath granted us a longer Reſpite (who have long ſince deſerved Ruin) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues his <hi>Warnings,</hi> when our <hi>Puniſhment</hi> was ſo ready to fall down on our heads, and which nothing but the watchfull eye of Providence could have reſcued from! 'Twas only God <hi>(in whoſe hands the hearts of all men are to turn as the Rivers of Water)</hi> that turned the hearts of ſome of the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> themſelves to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come our <hi>Deliverers:</hi> Fetching Good out of Evil; and, by a miracle of Providence, ſecuring both our <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> in the Truſt only of thoſe, that were pitch'd upon as fitteſt to be entruſted with the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of the worſt of Villanies!</p>
            <p>For what greater Evil could men contrive, or have we to fear, than <hi>the Aſſaſſination of his Majeſty's perſon, to make way for a foreign Invaſion, whereby to enſlave both our Bodies and Souls!</hi> Yet this is what was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned for us, and what God hath ſhewn himſelf ſo ſignally in the Diſcovery of what we are now Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled here to return him Thanks for.</p>
            <p>To Him therefore be render'd all the Praiſe, and our heartieſt Thanks for this his infinite Goodneſs to us! That he ſtill ſhews his Almighty Hand in our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109695:15"/>
by which he wrought out, at firſt, our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance! That he hath hitherto prevented our <hi>Return to Bondage,</hi> and ſtill continues us on the Borders of the <hi>Land of Reſt,</hi> and hath not yet, after all, taken from us our Hopes of a ſeaſonable entrance and happy ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement therein! That He hath preſerved to us his own <hi>Anointed, the Breath of our Noſtrils,</hi> and the <hi>Light of Iſrael,</hi> continuing the ſame miraculous Providence that hath ſhewn it ſelf in ſo many wonderfull Deliverances, thro' the whole courſe of his Life, to encircle ſtill his Head, both as an <hi>Ornament</hi> and <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met,</hi> beſpeaking him no leſs the Darling and Care of Heaven, than expoſing him to be the Envy and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Earth! <hi>Oh that Men would therefore praiſe the Lord for his Goodneſs, and declare the Wonders that he doth for the Children of Men!</hi> That he doth for his Anointed! And hath now once more done for Us in preſerving him from thoſe bloody Deſigns which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but his own Infinite Wiſdom and Power could have diſcovered and defeated! <hi>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us; but unto thy Name be aſcribed all Honour, Glory and Praiſe,</hi> with moſt humble and hearty Thanks in all Churches of the Saints: Even ſo, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord our God, who only doth wondrous things; and bleſſed be the Name of his Majeſty for ever!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſurely is our Duty hence to <hi>Heaven,</hi> whence our Mercy comes; and which, if duly perform'd, will influence our Behaviour here towards his <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> to whom it more immediately was directed. For this, finally, inſtructs us,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſtly, <hi>To Confirm and Strengthen more our Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to the preſent Government for the future.</hi> For to this end God ſeems to have brought it into ſo Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Danger, and to have ſo eminently reſcued it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109695:15"/>
therefrom; to let us ſee its Worth, and how dear it is to Him, and to endear it hereby to us. For <hi>the true worth of a Mercy is never valued,</hi> we ſay, <hi>till loſt:</hi> And therefore, tho' we have not yet loſt ours, yet by the Danger it was in to be loſt, God hath made us very ſenſible of the Evil it would have been to us; and hereby hath taught us the more to value it.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore, at laſt, perſuade our ſelves not only to be <hi>reconciled</hi> to the Government God hath put us under, and would do us good by; but to <hi>endear</hi> it to us, and unite and firmly <hi>Aſſociate</hi> our ſelves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and ſupport it, ſince God appears ſo eminently for it, and calls to us by ſuch repeated Providences to do ſo too. Let us look up to God, and take our mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures from him; to ſubmit to his <hi>Councils,</hi> and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to permit him to govern the World and Us, by the <hi>Captain</hi> of his own <hi>appointment:</hi> Laying aſide our Prejudices and Paſſions, Rancor and <hi>Rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> let us, at leaſt, hearken to the ſeaſonable Advice of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> Act. 5.35, 38, 39. <hi>Ye Men of Iſrael, take heed to your ſelves what ye intend to do as touching theſe Men.—Refrain from theſe Men, and let them alone; for if this Council or this Work be of Men, it will come to naught: But if it be of God, ye cannot over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw it, leſt haply ye be found even to fight againſt God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ever Prince in the World was own'd to be of God, then ſurely is Ours; by a continued Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch Providences to <hi>Preſerve</hi> him and <hi>Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point</hi> his Enemies. And may God ſtill continue the ſame Miracle of Protection of him to us! And add One more, in uniting all the Hearts and Affections of this whole Nation to him! that ſo he may hencefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, without any Diſcouragement or Interruption
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109695:16"/>
go on to perfect the Deliverance he is engag'd in for us; and not only ſecure us from ever <hi>returning</hi> again <hi>in Rebellion, to Bondage;</hi> but ſpeedily bring us into the <hi>Land of Reſt</hi> (our <hi>Sins</hi> hitherto have only delay'd our entrance into) and ſecure to us, inviolably, our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Rights</hi> by a laſting advantageous <hi>Peace;</hi> and after a long and happy Reign on Earth, be late admitted to a Glorious and Everlaſting Kingdom in Heaven! And let all the People ſay, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109695:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
